# Denis Sergeev

My interests include exoplanet atmospheric dynamics, general circulation of the atmosphere, polar meteorology. Most of my current research focuses on the atmospheric modelling of terrestrial planets. I hope to contribute to our understanding of the climate regimes on different planets and their potential for habitability.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2018–2021 **Postdoctoral Research Fellow** | Climate modelling of terrestrial exoplanets | *University of Exeter* Exeter, United Kingdom

## **EDUCATION**

2014–2018 PhD in Meteorology | University of East Anglia | Norwich, United Kingdom

Supervisors: Prof. Ian A. Renfrew • Prof. Thomas Spengler • Prof. Stephen Dorling

Thesis title: Characteristics of polar lows in the Nordic Seas and the impact of orography and sea ice on their development

- Analysis of high-resolution model simulations
- Model skill verification against aircraft and satellite observations
- Sensitivity to orography and sea ice distribution
- Statistical analysis of cyclone climatology

2009–2014 Specialist Diploma in Meteorology | With Honours | Lomonosov Moscow State University | Moscow, Russia Supervisor: Dr. Victor Stepanenko

Thesis title: Idealised numerical modelling of polar mesocyclone dynamics

- · Idealised baroclinic channel simulations
- Testing different parameterizations and experiment set-ups
- · Energy and vorticity budgets

### INTERNSHIPS

Oct 2013 Visiting student | Geophysical Institute | University of Bergen | Bergen, Norway Supervisor: Prof. Thomas Spengler

Jul 2012 Intern | Laboratory of Climate Theory | A.M. Obukhov Institute of Atmospheric Physics | Moscow, Russia Supervisor: Dr. Alexey Eliseev

## PUBLICATIONS

#### Peer-reviewed

- 7. **Sergeev, D.E.**, I.A. Renfrew, T. Spengler, A. Terpstra, and S.-I. Watanabe. 2019. North Atlantic polar mesoscale cyclones in ERA5 and ERA-Interim reanalyses. *Geophysical Research Letters*, under review
- 6. Renfrew, I.A., R.S. Pickart, K. Våge, G.W. Moore, T.J. Bracegirdle, A.D. Elvidge, E. Jeansson, T. Lachlan-Cope, L. McRaven, L. Papritz, J. Reuder, H. Sodemann, A. Terpstra, S. Waterman, H. Valdimarsson, A. Weiss, M. Almansi, F. Bahr, A. Brakstad, C. Barrell, J.K. Brooke, B. Brooks, I.M. Brooks, M.E. Brooks, E.M. Bruvik, C. Duscha, I. Fer, H.M. Golid, M. Hallerstig, I. Hessevik, J. Huang, L. Houghton, S. Jónsson, M. Jonassen, K. Jackson, K. Kvalsund, E.W. Kolstad, K. Konstali, J. Kristiansen, R. Ladkin, P. Lin, A. Macrander, A. Mitchell, H. Olafsson, A. Pacini, C. Payne, B. Palmason, M.D. Pérez-Hernández, A.K. Peterson, G.N. Petersen, M.N. Pisareva, J.O. Pope, A. Seidl, S. Semper, D.E. Sergeev, S. Skjelsvik, H. Søiland, D. Smith, M.A. Spall, T. Spengler, A. Touzeau, G. Tupper, Y. Weng, K.D. Williams, X. Yang, and S. Zhou. 2019. The Iceland Greenland Seas Project. Bulletin of American Meteorological Society, accepted
- 5. **Sergeev, D.E.**, I.A. Renfrew, and T. Spengler. 2018. Modification of polar low development by orography and sea ice. *Monthly Weather Review*, 146: 3325–3341
- 4. Shestakova, A.A., P.A. Toropov, V.M. Stepanenko, **D.E. Sergeev**, and I.A. Repina. 2018. Observations and modelling of downslope windstorm in Novorossiysk. *Dynamics of Atmospheres and Oceans*, 83: 83–99
- 3. Sergeev, D.E., I.A. Renfrew, T. Spengler, and S.R. Dorling. 2017. Structure of a shear-line polar low. *Quaterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society*, 143(702): 12–26

- 2. Spengler, T., I.A. Renfrew, A. Terpstra, M. Tjernström, J. Screen, I.M. Brooks, A. Carleton, D. Chechin, L. Chen, J. Doyle, I. Esau, P.J. Hezel, T. Jung, T. Kohyama, C. Lüpkes, K.E. McCusker, T. Nygård, D.E. Sergeev, M.D. Shupe, H. Sodemann, and T. Vihma. 2016. High Latitude Dynamics of Atmosphere-Ice-Ocean Interactions. *Bulletin of American Meteorological Society*, 97(9): ES179–ES182
- 1. Eliseev, A.V., **D.E. Sergeev**. 2014. Impact of Subgrid Scale Vegetation Heterogeneity on the Simulation of Carbon Cycle Characteristics. *Izvestiya*, *Atmospheric and Oceanic Physics*, 50(3): 259–270

#### Proceedings

- 3. Sergeev, D.E., Stepanenko VM. 2013. Numerical modelling of polar mesocyclones generation mechanisms. *International Conference "Turbulence, atmosphere and climate dynamics" dedicated to A.M. Obukhov*, Selected papers: 168–170
- 2. **Sergeev, D.E.**, Zamyatina MY, Stepanenko VM. 2013. Thermal regime features of Kronotsky lake (in Russian). *Kronotsky State Natural Biosphere Reserve Proceedings*, 3: 29–41
- 1. Sergeev, D.E., Stepanenko VM. 2012. Parameterization of mesoscale sensible heat and methane fluxes in the region of Western Siberia. *International Conference and Early Career Scientists School on Environmental Observations, modelling and Information Systems (ENVIROMIS-2012)*, Selected papers: 67–69

### CONFERENCES

#### Oral presentations

- Aug 2019 Simulations of moist convection on tidally-locked rocky exoplanets | Exoclimes V | Oxford, UK
- Jun 2019 North Atlantic polar mesoscale cyclones in ERA5 and ERA-Interim reanalyses | IGP workshop | Norwich, UK
- Apr 2019 Atmospheric convection on tidally-locked Earth-like exoplanets | UK Exoplanet Community Meeting | London, UK
- Jun 2018 Modification of Polar Low Development by Sea Ice and Svalbard Orography | POLAR2018 | Davos, Switzerland
- Oct 2017 The influence of Svalbard orography and sea ice on polar low development | 18th Cyclone Workshop | Sainte-Adèle, Canada
- Apr 2017 Polar lows and how background environment can influence their development | Cambridge Earth Systems Science EnvEast Doctoral Alliance Symposium | Cambridge, UK
- May 2016 Structure of the shear-line polar low south of Svalbard | NORPAN kick-off meeting | Tokyo, Japan
- Apr 2016 Structure of the shear-line polar low south of Svalbard | 13th European Polar Lows Working Group (EPLWG) Workshop | Paris, France

#### Poster presentations

- Jul 2015 Structure and dynamics of a shear-line polar low during a cold-air outbreak over the Norwegian Sea | Royal Meteorological Society Student Conference | Birmingham, UK
- Mar 2015 Structure and dynamics of a shear-line polar low during a cold-air outbreak over the Norwegian Sea | Dynamics of Atmosphere-Ice-Ocean Interactions in the High Latitudes workshop | Rosendal, Norway
- May 2014 Numerical modelling of polar mesocyclones dynamics diagnosed by the energy budget | European Geosciences Union (EGU) General Assembly | Vienna, Austria
- Apr 2013 Impact of subgrid-scale vegetation heterogeneity on results of climate model simulation of carbon cycle | European Geosciences Union (EGU) General Assembly | Vienna, Austria
- Apr 2013 Numerical modelling of polar mesocyclones generation mechanisms | European Geosciences Union (EGU) General Assembly | Vienna, Austria

# AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

- 2017 Best Presentation Award | Cambridge Earth Systems Science EnvEast Doctoral Alliance (CEEDA) Symposium
- 2016 Travel Bursary | WWRP/WCRP/Bolin Center Polar Prediction School
- 2015 Travel Award | Dynamics of Atmosphere-Ice-Ocean Interactions in the High Latitudes workshop
- 2014–2018 Lord Zuckerman scholarship | School of Environmental Sciences, University of East Anglia
  - 2014 Young Scientist's Travel Award (YSTA) | European Geosciences Union (EGU) General Assembly
  - 2014 Russian Academy of Sciences Young Scientist Medal

# SUPERVISION OF STUDENTS

2019 Isobel Parry | Summer student | University of Exeter | Water cycle on Proxima Centauri b

2018-2019 Jake Eager | MSc | University of Exeter | Implications of Stellar Type on the Habitability of Tidally Locked Terrestrial Exoplanets

### COMPUTER SKILLS

**Operating systems:** *Linux* • Unix • Windows **Computer languages:** *Python* • Fortran

**Data visualisation**: Python • Matlab • NCL • Paraview

Parallel programming: Dask • MPI • OpenMP Version control systems: Git • Subversion Document preparation: LaTeX • Markdown

## LANGUAGES

Russian: Native speaker

**English:** Fluent **French:** Basic

# **VOCATIONAL TRAINING**

Jul 2019 2nd ICTP Summer School on Theory, Mechanisms and Hierarchical Modelling of Climate Dynamics: Convective Organization and Climate Sensitivity

Apr 2018 Fortran Modernisation Workshop

Apr 2016 WWRP/WCRP/Bolin Center Polar Prediction School

Dec 2014 UK Met Office Unified Model Training

Sep-Dec 2011 Global Climate Change course

#### EnvEast Doctoral Training Partnership (DTP)

Jun 2017 Weather presenting course

Jan 2017 Raspberry Pi course

#### Safety training

Feb 2017 Level 1 First Aid for Field Work course

Dec 2017 Sea Survival course

Jan 2018 Helicopter Underwater Escape Training Course (CA-EBS)

# FIELDWORK EXPERIENCE

Feb-Mar 2018 The Iceland-Greenland Seas Project (IGP) field campaign | Characterising the atmospheric forcing and the ocean response of coupled atmosphere-ocean processes; in particular cold-air outbreaks in the vicinity of the marginal ice zone and their triggering of oceanic heat loss and the generation of dense water masses | Akureyri, Iceland

Aug 2012 Field practice in meteorology | Study of prevailing mesoscale processes via wind characteristic measurements and lake hydrothermodynamical modelling | Kronotsky National Reservation, Kamchatka pen., Russia

Jan-Feb 2012 Field practice in meteorology | Measurements of the convective boundary layer over the polynya | White Sea Biological Station, Karel Republic, Russia

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Jan 2018 ECR course "Introduction to Python in Environmental Sciences" | Course leader | University of East Anglia | Norwich, UK

2015–2017 **Teaching assistance** | Modelling Environmental Processes, Meteorology, Numerical Skills for Scientists | University of East Anglia | Norwich, UK

Apr 2017 Field course teaching assistance | University of East Anglia | Slapton, UK

Nov 2016 Python training course | Course leader | University of East Anglia | Norwich, UK

# **EDITORIAL SERVICE**

Acted as

reviewer for Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society (x3)

## OUTREACH

2019 School outreach programme "Exoplanet Explorers"

· Visit to Pool Academy

2014–2015 Contributor to SciSnack blogging platform

- Disastrous Disaster Movies
- Polar Lows: What Fuels Arctic Hurricanes?
- · Worldwide Weird Weather Words

# VOCATIONAL EXPERIENCE

Apr–Jun 2018 Data technician | Processing of meteorological data collected in the IGP field campaign | University of East Anglia

2015–Present Python group leader | Founder and leader of the Python programming language users group | University of East Anglia

Mar 2015 Rapporteur | Dynamics of Atmosphere-Ice-Ocean Interactions in the High-Latitudes workshop | Rosendal, Norway

Aug-Sep 2013 Weather Forecaster | Forecast and Briefing Service | Main Aviation Meteorological Centre, Vnukovo Airport

## REFERENCES

**Dr F Hugo Lambert** University of Exeter f.h.lambert@exeter.ac.uk Prof lan Renfrew University of East Anglia i.renfrew@uea.ac.uk **Prof Thomas Spengler** University of Bergen thomas.spengler@uib.no